Okay, בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody. We,
today's דף daf is ע"ב, Ayin Bet, 72. And we pick up
at the very bottom of ע"א עמוד ב'. Ayin Aleph Amud Bet.
And we are in the middle of discussing the concept of טומאה
בלועה, tuma blua, of swallowed טומאה. tuma. If something טמא tamei is
in a body, in a person's body or in an animal's body,
the טומאה, tuma, it's like it doesn't exist. The טומאה tuma doesn't
go out. It's not just that he's not touching it, but even
if it's something like a dead body, like the fetus in the
mother's womb, which causes טומאה tuma in the room, it doesn't cause
טומאה tuma if it's in a person's body, if it's in the
mother's body. And similarly, if there's טהרה בלועה, tahara blua, something that's
not טמא tamei in a person's body, then even if the person
becomes טמא, tamei, that thing remains unaffected. Okay, so that was stated
by רבא, Rava, and he proved it from various פסוקים psukim or
whatever. And רבא Rava said, what's the big חידוש? chiddush? It's an
explicit משנה mishnah in מקואות Mikvaot that speaks about this, about a
ring that's טמא tamei that's in a person's body or that's טהור
tahor and it's in a person's body. And basically, it's already all
there. So what's the big חידוש chiddush about רבא? Rava? And now
we are going to see the answer right now. So let's take
a look. So the גמרא Gemara says, three lines from the bottom
of ע"א עמוד ב', Ayin Aleph Amud Bet, כי קאמר
רבה, ki ka'mar Rabba, no, in what was רבה Rabba talking about?
What was his special case that he was telling me something that
was not in the משנה? mishnah? כגון שבלע שתי טבעות, kegon shebala
shtei tabaot, somebody swallowed two rings, presumably sequentially, not at the same
time. אחת טמאה, achat tmea, first one that was טמאה, tmea, let's
say it's something that had touched a dead body and had the
same טומאה tuma as a corpse. ואחת טהורה, ve'achat tehora, and then
afterwards he swallowed another ring. Maybe it was a ring-eating contest or
something, I don't know.
And now the question is, so to say the person isn't טמא
tamei with the טמא tamei ring that's inside of him, or I
mean, assuming, you know, if the way that he didn't touch it
or whatever, that he, some other circumstance, let's say he walked into
a room, other people don't become טמא, tamei, that we already said.
But here's רבה'ס Rabba's חידוש. chiddush. דלא מטמייא לה מטמאה לטהורה. dilo
metamaya la mitmea letehora. The two rings are sitting there in his
stomach, that maybe they're even touching. Nevertheless, the טמאה tmea one is
not מטמא metamei the טהורה tehora one. Which, which is a big
חידוש. chiddush. Which basically means that it's not just that the thing
that's swallowed in the body doesn't exist for people on the outside.
It means that once it's inside of a body, it's like it
doesn't exist to the entire world, even to the other ring on
the inside. Anything absorbed in a body is like it בכלל b'chlal
doesn't exist, even from the perspective of the other ring sitting in
the stomach. Now of course, the problem with that is that our
משנה mishnah seems to say exactly the opposite of that. Our משנה
mishnah said there's a dead fetus in a woman's body, and the
woman is טהורה tehora because it doesn't affect her, because from the
perspective of the outside, it's like it's not there yet. But from
the perspective of the midwife who sticks her hand in and touches
it, the midwife is טמאה. tmea. So that, the midwife's hand inside
is just like the other ring in the stomach, excuse the analogies
here and the human tragedy that we're talking about, but if we
can bracket that, so the point is, is that it does seem
to be, you know, that even from the perspective of something that's
also inside, from the perspective of something inside, it does exist. So
how could רבה Rabba say this? Now by the way, I should
say that תוספות Tosafot also asks, not only how could רבה Rabba
say this, but how does he know it's true? And so okay,
that's his חידוש, chiddush, but where's he getting it from if it's
not in the other משניות? mishnayot? So תוספות Tosafot has an answer.
Because if you remember, one of the cases before was about somebody
who swallowed something טמא tamei and it says he can go ahead
and eat תרומה. terumah. So the question is, why can he eat
תרומה, terumah, right? It's okay that, that, that, that the thing טמא
tamei in his stomach doesn't make things on the outside טמא, tamei,
but if he eats תרומה terumah it'll go into his stomach and
it'll touch the טמא tamei thing in his stomach. So תוספות Tosafot
says that's where רבה Rabba learned that idea, that even from the
perspective of two things in the stomach, a טמא tamei and a
טהור, tahor, the טמא tamei is not מטמא metamei the טהור. tahor.
Once it's in a body, it's like it doesn't exist even from
the perspective of the inside. So now the question is going to
be, how is that different than the midwife and the fetus?
Yes, we just, for two issues? Yeah. Do we say that in,
let's say, like, you know, like a fish, a kosher fish swallows
a טרף treif fish and it's still in?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, those are right, those are interesting other questions about,
you know, animals eating and what stage, you know, does it get
digested that it's not considered really. But that's also when you open
it up and it becomes exposed to the outside world at that
stage. But that is an interesting comparison, yes. But here we're talking
about טומאה tuma and טהרה. tahara. Are we going to get to
that? Yes, in a much later פרק, perek, you know, not in
direct conversation with that. So now the גמרא Gemara asks this question.
So let's take a look at the top of ע"ב עמוד א'.
Ayin Bet Amud Aleph. והעובר והחיה, veha'ubar vehachaya, the case of the
fetus, the dead fetus in the mother's womb and the midwife, כשתי
טבעות דמי, keshtei tabaot dami, it's like two rings in somebody's stomach,
a טמא tamei ring and a טהור tahor ring, meaning it's from
the perspective of the inside, not the perspective of the outside. And
what do we say? וקמטמאה ליה עובר לחיה. vekamitamela ubar lachaya. And
the fetus makes the midwife טמאה. tmea. So it almost says exactly
the opposite. The mother is טהורה, tehora, but from the perspective of
the midwife who's handling it, right, it's like it is no longer
absorbed because they're in the same space. So that's like the two
rings and there we say that it, it does create טומאה tuma
to something that is in the same space. So how is that
different than
רבה'ס Rabba's case of... אמר רבא שאני עובר הא וסופו לצאת. Amar
Rava shani ubar ha ve-sofo latzeis. Oh no, an עובר, ubar, a
fetus is טמא tamei for people that are in its space, not
for the mother but for the midwife, because it's not totally going
to stay in the body. It's on its way out. Like a
ring in the esophagus? No, it's on its way out, it puts
it in the state where at least for its quasi-accessible so for
somebody who is accessing it, the midwife, it is considered and it
is considered no longer absorbed and it is טמא. tamei. But as
Michael says, okay, a ring that's in your stomach is also on
the way out, through a different exit, but it's on its way
out. So the גמרא Gemara says, so the גמרא Gemara says אמר
רבא עובר סופו לצאת טבעת אין סופה לצאת? Amar Rava ubar sofo
latzeis taba'at ein sofo latzeis? What,
the fetus is on the way out and the ring isn't on
the way out? They're both on the way out, so what's the
difference? So the גמרא Gemara says אלא אמר רבא פומבדיתאי ידעי טעמא
דהאי מילתא. Ella amar Rava Pumpedisa'ei yadei ta'ama de-hai milsa. The Pumpeditian
knows the explanation of this, of this. Who's the Pumpeditian? ומנו רב
יוסף. Umanhu Rav Yosef. So רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, who was רבא's
Rava's contemporary and רבא's, Rava's, one of רבא's Rava's teachers, says it's
funny that he calls him that way, it seems a little bit,
you know, of something more you would refer to a colleague that
way, not a רב, rav, not a רבי, rebbe, but anyway, so
he knows how to explain this issue about how come the midwife
is טמאה, tmeia, but the ring according to רבא, Rava, if two
rings are in the stomach, one טמא tamei one טהור, tahor, they
don't affect one another. So what's the explanation?
דאמר רב יוסף אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל טומאה זו אינה מדברי
תורה אלא מדברי סופרים. De-amar Rav Yosef amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel
tumah zu einah mi-divrei Torah ella mi-divrei Sofrim. This טומאה tumah of
the midwife is only rabbinic. That really רבא Rava is right, that
something that is absorbed in a body is like for טומאה tumah
purposes like it doesn't exist even for something in the same space,
even for the other ring. So why do we say in our
משנה Mishnah that the midwife is טמאה? tmeia? That's only rabbinic. Why
is it rabbinic at all? Why did they do it there? So
מאי אינה מדברי תורה אלא מדברי סופרים? Mai einah mi-divrei Torah ella
mi-divrei Sofrim? So first the גמרא Gemara also says why do you
go to this long explanation, this is not biblical, it's only rabbinic,
just say it's rabbinic. The fact that you're saying, making this big
statement it's not biblical seems like there's something else that's bothering you.
So the גמרא Gemara says דלא תימא אליבא דרבי עקיבא דאמר עובר
במעי אשה טמא. Delo teima aliba de-Rabbi Akiva d'amar ubar me'ei ishah
tamei. Don't say that our משנה Mishnah is like רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva that says the עובר ubar even when it's in the mother's
womb,
again a dead עובר ubar causes טומאה, tumah, אלא אפילו רבי ישמעאל
דאמר עובר במעי אשה טהור. ella afilu Rabbi Yishmael d'amar ubar me'ei
ishah tahor. Even according to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, we're going to
see the רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael in a
minute, who says that the dead עובר ubar is טהור, tahor, which
is what we've been assuming vis-a-vis the mother and even vis-a-vis the
midwife. So nevertheless, even though it should not yet cause
טומאה, tumah, nevertheless גזרו בה טומאה מדרבנן. gazru bah tumah mi-derabbanan. The
rabbis did say it would be טמא. tamei. Why? מאי טעמא? Mai
ta'ama? What's the reason why it's different than the two rings? So
אמר רב הושעיה גזירה שמא יוציא פלד ראשו חוץ לפרוזדור. Amar Rav
Hoshaya gezeirah shema yotzi pevah rosho chutz l'prozdor. So it says it's
not because it's eventually going to come out and that may be
the basis even biblically to distinguish. No, no, no, the ring will
eventually come out as well. It's that the עובר ubar is in
the process of coming out. Since it's in the process of coming
out, so you know, this was sort of Rivka, this was your
question yesterday. Well, no, your question yesterday was how do you know
if it's dead or not. So here's the question is how do
you know if it's come out yet or not? Right? How do
you know yet, you know, at what stage you might think that
it has yet the head come out, now you'll say that's obvious,
maybe it's a little more obvious when the head comes out, but
nevertheless the גמרא's Gemara's concern was if you're handling it in the
process of coming out, if we were to say that you're טהור
tahor as long as it hasn't emerged, so then you might think
you're טהור tahor and you won't just pay the attention that you
were handling it, you weren't looking for a second and the head
popped out for a second or something of that nature. So therefore,
since it's in the process of coming out, we had to say
the midwife was טמאה tmeia even if she touched it on the
inside because it might have popped out and been on the outside
for a second.
So based on that, if they're just doing a regular exam, like
you know, a six months exam, she should be טהור, tahor, right?
Right. Exactly. And found that it was dead and they weren't in
the process then of trying to extract it. Once you're in the
process of extracting it, it says that's where it's different. So it's
a special דרבנן, derabbanan, right. So the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי,
I hachi, says the גמרא, Gemara, if that's true, אשה נמי, ishah
nami, so why do we say the woman is טהור? tahor? Say
the woman is, the mother is טמאה tmeia because maybe also the
baby will stick its head out and she won't realize once it's
in the process of coming out. So make the mother טמאה tmeia
as well. So the גמרא Gemara says אשה, ishah, the mother, מרגשת
בעצמה, margeshes b'atzmah, will have, will sense when the baby has emerged.
Okay, therefore for the mother we can say as long as it
hasn't emerged, you're טהורה, tehorah, once it's emerged, you're טמאה tmeia and
she will know when that moment is. But the midwife, it's not
her own body, she's handling the baby, she might not notice. So
the גמרא Gemara says ותימא לה לחיה, Veseima lah l'chaya, so have
the mother tell the midwife when the baby has emerged! If you're
concerned that the midwife will maybe think one thing and it's the
other. Have the mother tell her when it happened since the mother
knows. So the גמרא Gemara says טרידא, trida, no, the mother is
a little preoccupied, so she might not be exactly focused on telling
the midwife when this occurs. So for her we can say, if
you know that it occurred, you know, before the head came out,
whenever, you know, well actually the funny thing is that she's going
to be טמאה temei'ah eventually anyway once it comes out, but the
question is at what moment, you know, was it at 11:00 a.m.,
was it at noon, at what moment? So for her we can
say when did you sense the head coming out. But for the
midwife, she might think one thing and it's really the other, so
we're just going to tell her you're טמאה temei'ah once you were
handling it. But the basic principle is surprisingly that this idea of
טומאה בלועה tumah beluah really in principle applies even if both things
are in the same space. Even for the midwife's hands that are
in the, in the uterus, even for the two rings that are
in the stomach, even for things that are in the same space,
once it's absorbed in the body it doesn't exist even for something
sharing the space. And the only reason the midwife is טמאה temei'ah
in this case is because she might not realize that the baby
has emerged. Yes. Does this principle
apply to a buried מת? met? A buried—no, no, בלועה beluah is
only—is only absorbed in a person's body. I mean, for example, the
whole phrase the גמרא Gemara used yesterday, which is טומאה רצוצה בוקעת
ועולה, tumah retzutzah boka'at ve'olah, a pressed down טומאה tumah bursts forth,
refers exactly to like buried in the ground, which is why, you
know, there's a whole problem about planes flying over cemeteries, because the
טומאה tumah goes through the basically ground and you know up to
the, you know, would hit the plane essentially. And then there's a
question, you know, so there's all questions about that. If there's an
אהל, ohel, it's different, but you can't—that the אהל ohel stops it,
but you can't consider a coffin an אהל ohel because a coffin
is considered like an extension of the corpse itself. So anyway, but
no, it's only specifically about absorbed in a body, okay, buried in
a body.
Is there any distinction between whether the rings are touching or they're
not?
No, even if they're touching, yeah, which is an amazing thing. These
two rings are touching, but because it didn't happen as it were
on the outside world where we have access, you know, if you
want, maybe this is a helpful way of thinking about it, the
same way we sort of
say
like—no, no—the same way we say we don't pay attention to things
that are microscopic, right? We don't have to worry about microscopic bugs,
right? The תורה Torah doesn't sort of acknowledge, you know, not that
they don't exist, but they're not sort of, you know, real enough
to us to be—to have a הלכה halachah status. So it's saying
something similar here. If it's within a person's body, right, it does
not yet, you know, it's not—so even though there's touching in the
body, they're not outside, we don't have access to them, you know,
they don't—they don't yet exist. But again, that's within טומאה וטהרה, tumah
vetaharah, right? We don't take it to an extreme, because then you
would say so a fetus, you know, has no—there's no status to
a fetus because it's not yet outside. And we don't say that.
Whether it's an abortion question or other legal questions, you know, there's
a whole range of issues that maybe a fetus does or does
not have different statuses. So you can't say it across the board,
but at least by טומאה. tumah.
Yes, I'm wondering why are the rabbis anxious to impose an extra
strictness on the midwives which the תורה Torah did—there now, is not
according to תורה, Torah, we're just adding, we just decided to—well,
it's—it's a normal concern about things that people, you know, assume one
thing and they often make mistakes and we have to play it
safe. Is your concern that this would discourage people from getting into
the business? Well, everybody is going to be טמא מת tamei met
anyway, if it's a miscarriage, the mother's going to be טמא מת,
tamei met, the midwife's going to be טמא מת, tamei met, everybody's
going to be it anyway. The question is just at what stage,
five minutes earlier or five minutes later. Right, and as very little
impact. Exactly. It's really no—for us in a post-מקדש Mikdash time there's
like no practical impact. In the time of a מקדש Mikdash it
would be a question that if she became טמאה temei'ah and then
took a break, which she—and she, you know, she happened to be
married to a כהן, kohen, could she take a break and go
eat her תרומה terumah sandwich and come back? You know? But really,
at the end of the day, for us in post-מקדש Mikdash there's
very little relevance and also, right, everybody's going to be טמא מת
tamei met anyway. It's a question about five minutes earlier. And we're
always imposing strictures to where we play things safe.
But sometimes we try to be מיקל. meikel.
I understand, but I'm saying when we have, you know, doubts and
there's a general, a reasonable concern that people will make a mistake
and to play it safe. You're right, we can't consistently say when
do the rabbis tend to be strict, when do they not. But
I don't see this as unusual at all.
Yeah, the rest of it's based on policy but it seems
to discourage
midwife—discourage the profession, discourage the intervention if it's appropriate.
Right, but I'm—but as you
read this and you read this and you really wonder whether these
guys ever actually
handled a birth.
But—but again, the point is that if it was—is she going to
be טמאה temei'ah at all or not, and a midwife was saying
you're going to make me טמאה temei'ah all the time, who needs
this profession? But if every time there's a miscarriage she becomes טמא
מת, tamei met, and the only question is when do you assume
you're טמא מת, tamei met, you know, from the moment you handled
it as opposed to from the moment it came out, so it's
a question of, you know, an hour or so, you know, is
that really going to have such an impact on people's behavior?
We all know cases where somebody handles a miscarriage by themselves, and
it certainly would sound like this type of policy would encourage midwives
to—oh, I see.
You're—this is a miscarriage and go do it yourself.
How would she know if it's a miscarriage or... but you're saying,
let's say she knows, let's say you know it's a stillbirth, right?
There's no movement.
Right. But again, even without this, let's say they hadn't made this
policy. The midwife is going to be טמאה tme'ah when the baby
emerges.
Even if she's present.
Right, but you're saying what, that a midwife without this, a midwife
would come help the woman get the baby to the point of
almost emerging and then walk out of the room.
Well she wouldn't even come, she would she would listen for a
fetal heartbeat. Right. And say, you know what, you're going to have
a miscarriage, I'll see you later.
But I'm saying she'll say that anyway because even without this strictness
she'll be טמאה tme'ah once once the baby emerges.
She won't be there.
I understand. My point is is that it's not the rabbis now,
it's not the policy of making her טמאה tme'ah a little sooner
that's going to get her to leave the room. According to your
concern she would leave the room with or without this rabbinic ruling
because if she's around at a miscarriage, right, she's going to be
טמאה tme'ah anyway. That's my point. The only difference of this ruling
is that it makes her טמאה tme'ah a little bit sooner in
the process.
And it wouldn't motivate her to leave.
Right. So alright, I I hear. Alright let's go on. Now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. מאי Mai Rabbi Ishmael ומאי u'mai Rabbi
Akiva? What's the debate of Rabbi Ishmael and Rabbi Akiva? Because until
now it's like everybody agreed that the fetus inside the mother is
בלוע balua and it's not טמא. tamei. Now we're saying that there's
a position of Rabbi Akiva that it does cause טומאה tumah even
when it's in the mother. So let's take a look. דתניא, Detanya,
we taught in the ברייתא. braita. וכל אשר יגע על פני השדה.
Vechol asher yiga al p'nei hasadeh.
This is talking about טומאת מת, tumat meit, about a corpse, and
it says anything you touch on the on the field, בחלל חרב
או במת, be-chalal cherev o be-meit, in a somebody slayed by a
sword or a dead body, it says you know that you're טמא
tamei for seven days. That's the classic פרשה parsha there in חקת
Chukat about the טומאה tumah that is created through a dead body.
So anything you touch on the field which means like it's on
the outside, it's exposed, להוציא עובר במעי אשה, lehotzi ubar bemei isha,
דברי divrei Rabbi Ishmael, which excludes touching the fetus in the mother's
womb, that's the position of Rabbi Ishmael, that if that that is
that that is still טהור. tahor. In principle even the midwife is
טהור tahor when she touches it when it's still in the mother's
womb. So רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, no, that's not what
it's coming to do.
לרבות גולל ודופק, Lerabot golel ve-dofek, it's coming to include other things
that are on the field that are also טמא. tamei. What's the
גולל golel and דופק? dofek? There's a big debate, but רש"י Rashi
basically says it's like the headstone of a grave and the cover
of the coffin. That's sort of what I was saying before, that
the parts of the grave itself are considered to be an extension
of the very corpse, which is why the coffin does not prevent
the טומאה tumah from going up. So those things are also on
the field, especially if the field happens to be a cemetery, and
those are טמא tamei like the corpse itself. And that's why it's
saying on the field, but not to exclude something that is not
open, meaning something like the fetus in the mother's womb. So the
גמרא Gemara will say that. ורבי ישמעאל גולל ודופק, V'Rabbi Ishmael golel
ve-dofek, where does Rabbi Ishmael get the idea of the גולל golel
ודופק, ve-dofek, the headstone and the coffin lid? הלכתא גמירי לה. Hilcheta
gmiri lah. That's a הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha leMoshe miSinai. He doesn't
get it from a פסוק. pasuk. ורבי עקיבא ועובר במעי אשה טמא
מדאורייתא מנא ליה? V'Rabbi Akiva ve-ubar bemei isha tamei mide'oraita m'na lei?
And Rabbi Akiva, which is more or less what Michael said, what
is motivating him not to read the verse like Rabbi Ishmael? Why
does why does what's motivating him to say that a fetus even
in the mother's womb causes טומאה tumah if it's obviously a dead
fetus?
אמר רב אושעיא, Amar Rav Oshaya, אמר קרא, amar kra, the verse
says הנוגע במת בנפש, Hanogei bemeit benefesh, if anybody touches a dead
body בנפש אדם benefesh adam of a human.
Now you'll
remember we're going to play around with the ב be again, the
same way we said בהמה בבהמה, behema be-behema, right, which an animal
we read it to mean it wasn't the פשט, pshat, but an
animal in an animal, the שחיטה shechita works for an animal in
an animal, a fetus. Here we're reading במת בנפש. bemeit benefesh. It's
a dead body in some other soul. It is a fetus in
the mother. Okay. And nevertheless if you touch הנוגע במת בנפש, hanogei
bemeit benefesh, that if you touch it you are טמא, tamei, it
causes טומאה. tumah. איזו מת שבנפש של אדם? Eizo meit shebenefesh shel
adam? What's a case of a dead body in a person's body,
in another person? הוי אומר זה עובר שבמעי אשה. Hevei omer zeh
ubar she-be-mei isha. This is the fetus in the mother's womb. ורבי
ישמעאל, Ve-Rabbi Ishmael, what does Rabbi Ishmael do with that verse? ההוא
מיבעי ליה לרביעית דם הבא מן המת, Hahu mibai lei l'revi'it dam
haba min hameit, that not only does the body itself cause טומאה,
tumah, but even blood from a corpse, if it's a רביעית, revi'it,
which is very little, that's the amount with a רביעית revi'it of
a לוג, log, it's the amount we make קידוש kiddush on, about
three and a half ounces. So it's very little, but the rabbis
understood that that was the amount of blood that initially was within
a fetus when it was just born. So it understood that that
represented the amount of blood which life was dependent on. Okay. So
therefore that is a type of a נפש, nefesh, that is דם
הוא הנפש dam hu hanefesh also. So it might be playing off
of the word נפש. nefesh. So it's במת בנפש. bemeit benefesh.
Where is there an example of some type of a sense of
a dead body in a נפש, nefesh, in the blood that represents
the soul? So that is what it means. ההוא מיבעי ליה לרביעית
דם הבא מן המת. Hahu mibai lei l'revi'it dam haba min hameit.
A רביעית revi'it of blood that comes from a corpse שמטמא she-metamei
that it causes טומאה tumah just like the corpse itself. שנאמר, Shene'emar,
as the verse says הנוגע במת בנפש האדם. hanogei bemeit benefesh ha-adam.
You touch a corpse of a person's soul. So איזו נפש של
אדם, Eizu nefesh shel adam, what is the soul, right? הדם הוא
הנפש, hadam hu hanefesh, so what is the soul שמטמא? shemetamay? הוי
אומר, hevei omer, זו רביעית דם, zu revies dam, and that is
a רביעית revies of blood, three and a half ounces of blood.
So not to teach you a fetus in the mother's womb, that
is טהור, tahor, but to teach you something that is נפש nefesh
even the blood causes טומאה tumah of a dead body. רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, what does רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva get the idea, where
does he get the idea of blood לטמא? letamay? He goes according
to his reasoning that he says he learns it from another verse
and he even has a different ruling דאמר deamar who says אף
רביעית דם הבא משני מתים מטמא באהל. af revies dam habah mishnei
meisim metamei be'ohel. There is a debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
and רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. What if you had a רביעית revies
of blood that comes not from one body but it's half of
a רביעית revies from two separate bodies? Okay, so for example, right,
a כזית kezayis of a corpse causes טומאה. tumah. Let's say it's
from two separate corpses. Okay, would it or would it not? So
the question here as well is let's say the blood is from
two separate corpses. So רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says it does not
cause טומאה. tumah. It says בנפש אדם benefesh adam in singular, it
has to be one soul. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says even if
it comes from two corpses. Where does he know this? שנאמר shenemar
as the verse says ועל כל נפשות מת לא יבא, ve'al kol
nafshos meis lo yavo, all souls, dead souls you shall not come.
So again נפש nefesh meaning blood, but here it's in the plural.
So יבא yavo שני נפשות shnei nefashos לא יבא lo yavo שני
נפשות. shnei nefashos. There are two souls and here אחד echad but
it's sufficient that there's only one quantity because it's נפשות nafshos of
מת meis in the singular. So therefore that's where he learns the
idea of blood and he learns even from two separate bodies. So
basically they both agree to the idea of the גולל golel and
the דופק dofek of the headstone and the cover. They both agree
that blood causes טומאה tumah of a dead body except רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael says from one dead body, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
even if it's combined from two. The difference is that רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael says על פני השדה al pnei hasadeh means it has
to be out in the world and exposed, and רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva says no, even בנפש, benefesh, even a fetus causes טומאה. tumah.
Now the question is, does רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva disagree with everything
we've been talking about yesterday and today? Does he disagree with the
principle of טומאה בלועה, tumah bluah, absorbed טומאה? tumah? So רש"י Rashi
seems to say yes. Anyway, רש"י Rashi is a little complicated. תוספות
Tosafos has the best answer. תוספות Tosafos says there are different stages
when something is considered בלועה bluah as opposed to when something is
considered a baby is considered born, and they're not at the they
don't they're not contiguous. The baby is בלועה bluah when it's in
the mother's uterus. When the baby starts going through the vaginal canal,
through the birth canal, it's no longer בלועה. bluah. בלועה bluah means
it's very sort of deep in the body, that if somebody like,
you know, like if I put something in my mouth, okay, that's
בית הסתרים, beis hastarim, it's not on the outside, but it's not
בלועה. bluah. I open my mouth, you can see it. That's not
בלועה. bluah. בלועה bluah would have to get deeper in that it
could not be seen from the outside. So once the baby starts
coming down the birth canal, it's no longer בלועה bluah but it's
not yet born. Remember our משנה mishna said when is a baby
considered born? When the head emerges. So this is what תוספות Tosafos
says is the debate of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael and רבי עקיבא.
Rabbi Akiva. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says it's not בלועה bluah anymore,
it's in the birth canal, so if it's dead, it causes טומאה.
tumah. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says no, there's a special פסוק pasuk
that when it comes to a fetus, as long as it's not
born, we don't yet give it any sort of recognition in terms
of טומאה וטהרה. tumah vetaharah. So actually רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael is
the חידוש, chiddush, not רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
agrees to the principle of בלועה bluah but says once it's close
to coming out it's no longer בלועה bluah and it causes טומאה.
tumah. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says as long as the fetus hasn't
emerged, as long as it's not yet born, it's a special case
that it doesn't need to be בלועה bluah but it still doesn't
cause טומאה. tumah. And רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael is, you know, clearly
our משנה mishna because our משנה mishna seems to be well our
משנה mishna isn't explicit, but the sense one gets in our משנה
mishna is that the mother is not טמאה tmeiah until the baby
actually comes out. And that would be רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, but
that's after it stopped being בלועה. bluah. Alright, so that is the
debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. So
just to sum up what we said: we introduce a principle of
טומאה בלועה, tumah bluah, that it's absorbed, it doesn't cause טומאה tumah
and even in something that's in the same space, like two rings
in the stomach or the midwife's hand, you know, that is handling
the baby in the uterus, that does not cause טומאה. tumah. When
the baby, however, when it goes from the uterus to the birth
canal, it's no longer בלועה bluah but it's not yet born, that's
a debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael.
And when it emerges, certainly it causes טומאה. tumah. As I said,
it's interesting even though there are debates about, you know, abortion, and
some people would allow abortion in a wide range of circumstances according
to some, nevertheless, it still causes טומאה tumah of a מת meis
after it's developed to a certain point, which is quite fascinating. That's
in terms of humans are concerned. In terms of animals, although there
is a principle of טומאה בלועה tumah bluah by animals as well
as we said, the earlier משנה mishna said that if a fetus
is in an animal, it might be טהור, tahor, right? Why? Because
the same way the שחיטה shechitah of the mother makes the fetus
edible, so here the fetus inside of an animal, even for somebody
sticking their hand in, the case of the animals might be special
cases because the fetus actually can become even edible, so it might
even be
more. Yes.
Great, so then if I just want to make sure I understood
this, so let's say the fetus is not yet in the birth
canal but is dead and the midwife sticks her hand in it.
So biblically nothing because טומאה בלועה tuma belua even in things in
the same space is not a problem.
But rabbinically do we still have a גזירה? gezeira?
Yes. Yes. That's okay, so the rabbinic גזירה. gezeira.
And
and the אקנושתא Aknushta made it to the רביעית revi'it from two
מתים, meitim, so Rabbi Ishmael presumably would disagree with that? Correct. So
we just interpret the פסוק pasuk as sort of a
דאורייתא de'oraita of some kind? I guess. I guess. Okay. So now
we are done with טומאה בלועה tuma belua which is certainly challenging,
and now we but we are still not out of the woods
yet with טומאה. tuma. Okay. So let's take a look though, at
a case that I don't know, maybe a little bit easier. Let's
take a look at our famous case of the hand that is
stuck of the fetus calf that is sticking out of the mother's
womb. Let's take a look. בהמה behema so the משנה. mishna. בהמה
המקשה לילד, behema hamaksha leyeled, so a בהמה behema is having travails
in giving birth, which just means it's not all happening quickly. והוציא
עובר ידו vehotzi ubar yado and the fetus stuck its hand out.
וחתכה vechatacha and you are cutting it off because you're trying to
help the mother, you know, so the you're sort of dismantling the
fetus. Okay. ואז ve'az now remember that hand that has stuck out
is forbidden. It the שחיטה shechita never applied to it, number one,
and according to the גמרא gemara earlier based on the verse of
בשר בשדה טרפה, basar basade tereifa, it's forbidden just based on a
separate verse. Okay, so that hand was cut off. ואחר כך שחט
את אמו ve'achar kach shachat et imo and then the mother was
slaughtered. So הבשר טהור. habasar tahor. So the limb is טהור. tahor.
Why? Because the בשר basar not excuse me not the limb. Excuse
me. The the meat of the mother is טהור. tahor. The limb
is אבר מן החי. ever min hachai. You cut the limb off
while it was the mother was still live, the fetus was still
live or whatever, so the limb is אבר מן החי. ever min
hachai. The point is though that living things or living animals, living
people become טמא, tamei, but living animals don't become טמא. tamei. So
although that אבר מן החי ever min hachai was severed from the
cow, it did not make the cow טמא, tamei, the cow was
alive. Now the cow is שחט-ed, shachat so the meat is all
טהור. tahor. This limb that you cut off had never affected the
status of the cow. Now,
let's say שחט את אמו ואחר כך חתכה. shachat et imo ve'achar
kach chatacha. You slaughtered the mother and then you cut it off.
Now what is the status of this stuck-out limb when you slaughtered
the mother? The שחיטה... shechita... it's not אבר מן החי. ever min
hachai. You didn't cut it off when the animal was alive. The
שחיטה shechita of the mother didn't work for the limb, right? Everybody
gets the case, right? The fetus is inside, the limb is stuck
out, the שחיטה shechita of the mother worked for the fetus but
not for the limb of the fetus. So what is the status
of this thing? Well, what we have a category of things in
which שחיטה shechita didn't work for. What what do we call things
that שחיטה shechita didn't work for? נבלה, neveila, if there was never
a שחיטה. shechita. Or, what do we call something that there was
a שחיטה shechita but it wasn't effective? טריפה. tereifa. Now here's the
difference. Okay, do we say by the limb it's like there was
no שחיטה shechita for the limb and it's a נבלה, neveila, or
there was a שחיטה shechita because there was a שחיטה shechita on
the mother and on the fetus, it just didn't work for the
limb, and that would be more similar to a טריפה? tereifa? There
was a שחיטה shechita but it didn't work. What's the difference? The
difference is that a נבלה neveila causes טומאה. tuma. A טריפה tereifa
does not cause טומאה. tuma. So we have to decide what is
the status now of this limb. And now that everything is dead,
it's touching the meat of the of its of the parent fetus
and of the mother and so on, and would it would it
transfer טומאה tuma to now the kosher meat?
The first one was would cause
טומאה, tuma, but you cut it when the mother was alive. You
cut it off when the mother was alive, so that was אבר
מן החי. ever min hachai. אבר מן החי ever min hachai causes
טומאה, tuma, but it was cut off when the mother was alive.
Here they're touching and the mother is dead. Does is this limb
טמא tamei to be מטמא metamei now the remainder of the fetus
and the mother? So let's take a look. שחט את אמו ואחר
כך חתכה. shachat et imo ve'achar kach chatacha. You slaughtered the mother
and then you cut off the limb. היד... excuse me... הבשר מגע
נבלה neveila. דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. So Rabbi Meir says
the limb is a נבלה. neveila It never had a שחיטה shechita
done to the limb and therefore the meat that is touching the
limb, the other part of the fetus, is something that touched a
נבלה neveila. and is טמא. tamei. וחכמים אומרים vechachamim omrim and the
sages say, מגע טריפה שחוטה. maga tereifa shechuta. No, it's like it's
touching something that was a טריפה tereifa animal that was שחט-ed, shachat
which means an act of שחיטה shechita was done, right? Because the
act of שחיטה shechita was done, it just wasn't effective on the
limb, so that gives it the status of a טריפה, tereifa, not
the status of a נבלה. neveila It's not obviously technically a טריפה,
tereifa, but that's the logical box to put it in. Something that
had a שחיטה shechita done that was not effective. Okay, and therefore
it has no טומאה. tuma. So the גמרא gemara says why don't
you just say it's טהור? tahor? So it says well there may
be a little טומאה דרבנן, tuma derabbanan, but there's no real טומאה
tuma by a טריפה. tereifa. Okay, so that is the question. Is
this limb a נבלה neveila, or טריפה? tereifa? Now, now we're going
to see that now the משנה mishna sort of is a little
expands and we actually have a little bit of a spelled out,
you know, they get to it. Sometimes very often you don't have
them debating their point in a משנה, mishna, but here you do.
מה מצינו בטריפה ששחיטתה מטהרתה, ma matzinu betereifa sheshechitatah metaheratah, so now
on ע"ב עמוד ב', ayin bet amud bet, the rabbis are going
to defend their position. What's the story about a טריפה? tereifa? That
there's an act of שחיטה, shechita, it just didn't work, but there's
an act of שחיטה, shechita, and that purifies it, meaning prevents it
from being a נבלה, neveilah. and the animal is not טמא. tamei.
אף שחיטת בהמה תטהר את האבר, Af shechitat behema titaher et ha'eiver,
the שחיטה shechita of the mother, although it doesn't make the limb
edible, is enough that there was a שחיטה shechita and to say
that the limb is not a נבילה. neveila. Okay, so the limb
had a שחיטה shechita done that wasn't effective, which makes it a
טרפה, treifa, and like a טרפה, treifa, and therefore does not cause
טומאה. tumah. אמר להם רבי מאיר Amar lahem Rabbi Meir said back
Rabbi Meir to the sages: No, he said, לא, Lo, it's not
a good comparison. אם טיהרה שחיטת טרפה אותה, Im tihara shechitat treifa
ota, yes the שחיטה shechita of a טרפה treifa makes it טהור,
tahor, prevents it from becoming a נבילה neveila and from being טמא,
tamei, דבר שבגופה, davar she'be'gufah, that's because the שחיטה shechita was done
to its very body. So even though it wasn't effective, you could
still say a שחיטה shechita was done to this cow. However, לטהר
את האבר, l'taher et ha'eiver, do you think the שחיטה shechita of
the mother should purify, meaning prevent from becoming טמא tamei the limb,
דבר שאינה גופה, davar she'eina gufah, that is not part of the
body of the mother? He says the whole reason the שחיטה shechita
doesn't work on the stuck out limb is because we say that
stuck out limb is no longer part of the mother. So by
saying that or it's born, like לידה לאברים, leida l'eivarim, whatever. So
since that limb is no longer part of the mother, so the
שחיטה shechita did not apply to the limb. The שחיטה shechita only
applied to the mother, not to the limb. So as Rabbi Meir
says, so it's an interesting question, right? And to some degree, excuse
me, Michael might be right. It might be conceptually how do you
explain the problem? If you remember one explanation of the problem of
the limb was בשר בשדה טרפה. basar basadeh treifa. Well, just said
it went offside. Fine, offside. It doesn't mean that it's totally not
connected to the mother. It's been the wrong space for the שחיטה
shechita to work. So the שחיטה shechita could still be related to
it, but just not be effective for it because it's in the
wrong space. Whereas Rabbi Meir is saying it's no longer part of
the body and as Michael correctly says, the דף daf was done
on Shabbos, that could be the expression about יש לידה לאברים, yesh
leida l'eivarim, right? That it's like the limb has already been born.
It's coming out of the womb. It's like it's already been born.
So as far as the limb is concerned, it no longer relates
to the mother anymore. So that's what Rabbi Meir says. It's no
longer in any way connected to the mother so the שחיטה shechita
never even related to the limb and therefore it's a נבילה. neveila.
Okay.
So nobody says yes to Rabbi Meir's question? What? Nobody says yes
to Rabbi Meir's question.
Yes, what do you mean yes?
You know, should the שחיטה shechita purify the something that is outside,
the limb?
Oh, meaning say yes it's outside but nevertheless it works for it?
יש לידה לאברים. yesh leida l'eivarim. Right. It can't be viable. If
the rest of the body doesn't follow, it's not viable. It's not
the way of the world. It would seem like somebody should...
You mean you are saying that you could talk about a status
where it is not part of the body but because its health
depends on the body, that enough makes it related so the שחיטה
shechita of the mother applies to the limb.
At least until you cut it, it's attached.
Right, but just the physical attachment,
it's an integral piece.
Right, so even if... right. So that's the question, you know, when
the Rabbis disagreed to Rabbi Meir, did they disagree by saying you
say that it's not considered גופה, gufah, we say it is גופה?
gufah? Right, there's always the question, you know, which position did they
debate? Did they say we call it גופה, gufah, which is sort
of what I was suggesting, they would sort of say אין לידה,
ein leida, it's not considered לידה, leida, it's just בשר בשדה טרפה,
basar basadeh treifa, we call it גופה. gufah. Or would they say,
like what I think you were saying is, we'll admit that it's
not גופה, gufah, but even if it's not גופה, gufah, if it's
dependent on the mother and it's physically attached, even without calling it
גופה, gufah, that's enough to say the שחיטה shechita relates to it.
That's what you're suggesting, correct?
I'm just asking whether anybody takes the position.
Well, the גמרא... Gemara... it's never clear how the Rabbis reject Rabbi
Meir. Rabbi Meir says it's not the body. So what do the
Rabbis say? Do they say even though it's not the body, the
שחיטה shechita can work for it because it's enough connected to the
body, which is I believe what you're saying, or do they actually
say no, it is still considered the body, it's the body that
the שחיטה shechita doesn't work for, but it's still the body. So
they obviously say one or the other but they never fully articulate
which of the two points that they disagree with Rabbi Meir. So
let's take a look now how the debate continues. Now that we're
done with that, now we move away from Rabbi Meir and the
חכמים chachamim and we use it as an opportunity to explore the
very fact that a טרפה treifa is not טמא. tamei. Right, that
was everybody agreed to the fact that a טרפה treifa did not
cause טומאה, tumah, now but that's not explicit in the Torah. The
Torah speaks about a נבילה neveila causing טומאה, tumah, it never really
tells you what the story is about a טרפה. treifa. So let's
take a look at what the גמרא Gemara says here, at the
משנה, Mishna, how it's now it's going to use this as an
opportunity to spell that out. מניין לטרפה ששחיטתה מטהרתה? Menayin l'treifa she'shechitata
metaherata?
How do you know that the שחיטה shechita of an animal that's
a טרפה, treifa, that the meat is not טמא, tamei, it's not
treated like a נבילה? neveila? How do you know this principle that
everybody seems to agree to? So here's how you know it. בהמה
טמאה אסורה באכילה. Behema tmei'a asura ba'achila.
Excuse me, here's why you should say that it's not true, here's
the argument to say it's not true. Look at the case of
a non-kosher animal. A non-kosher animal can't be eaten. אף טרפה אסורה
באכילה, Af treifa asura ba'achila, and a טרפה treifa can't be eaten.
מה בהמה טמאה אין שחיטתה מטהרתה, Ma behema tmei'a ein shechitata metaherata,
if you did a שחיטה shechita on a non-kosher animal, on a
horse, let's say, okay, it would still cause טומאה, tumah, it's still
called
a נבילה, neveila, because it Let's say the same about a
כשר *kosher* animal. אף טריפה לא תטהרנה שחיטה *af treifa lo tetaherenna
shechita*.
Let's say that the שחיטה *shechita* of a טריפה *treifa*, it still
can't be eaten, so let's say that therefore it's like a נבלה
neveilah, *neveila* and it's טמא tamei *tamei*. What makes, why should it
be different? So the משנה Mishnah *Mishna* responds, it's all very interesting.
The משנה Mishnah: *Mishna*'s sort of arguing with its internal logic, right?
It's almost like the language of a מדרש הלכה *Midrash Halacha*. לא
*lo*, no. אם אמרת בבהמה טמאה שלא הייתה לה שעת הכושר *im
amarta be-behema tmeah she-lo hayta lah sha'at ha-kosher*. A non-כשר *kosher* animal
was never in the possible category of being eaten. Therefore, it's always
a נבלה neveilah. *neveila*. תאמר בטריפה *tomar be-treifa*, but a טריפה *treifa*,
שהייתה לה שעת הכושר *she-hayta lah sha'at ha-kosher*, when the animal was
born at least in theory it could have been eaten, and maybe
it only developed this טריפה *treifa* problem later. So since it was
once in the category of something that could be eaten, that's enough
to take it out of being considered a נבלה neveilah *neveila* once
it had a שחיטה *shechita*. So the גמרא Gemara: *Gemara*, so the
משנה mishna *Mishna* continues and says, טול לך מה שהבאת *tol lecha
ma she-heveta*. Okay, but you can't, take, fine, I'll concede the point.
Take what you've brought, meaning what were you trying to say? A
טריפה *treifa* that started life being כשר *kosher* should not cause טומאה
tumah *tumah*. Fine, but that only addresses some of the cases. טול
לך מה שהבאת *tol lecha ma she-heveta*, take what you brought. הרי
שנולדה טריפה מן הבטן מנין *harei she-noldah treifa min ha-beten minayin*? Let's
say an animal was born as a טריפה *treifa*. The animal was
born with a heart defect, okay? So therefore what makes it different
than a non-כשר *kosher* animal? A non-כשר *kosher* animal that's שחט shechted
*shecht*ed is a נבלה *neveila*. So an animal that's born as a
טריפה *treifa*, started its life not being able to be eaten, maybe
even if you שחט shechted *shecht* it should be considered like a
נבלה *neveila* and should cause טומאה tumah. *tumah*. So the משנה mishna,
*Mishna* says, לא *lo*, no, there's still a difference. אם אמרת בבהמה
טמאה שכן אין במינה שחיטה *im amarta be-behema tmeah she-ken ein be-minah
shechita*, תאמר בטריפה שיש במינה שחיטה *tomar be-treifa she-yesh be-minah shechita*. שחיטה
*shechita* is a meaningless act by non-כשר *kosher* animals, right? The whole
purpose of שחיטה *shechita* is to make something able to be eaten
by a Jew. Okay, right? So for non-Jews who don't have, you
know, they don't have כשר *kosher*, non-כשר *kosher*, they also don't have
שחיטה *shechita*. They just let the animal die and it's no longer
אבר ever, מן החי *ever min ha-chai*. So the whole concept of
שחיטה *shechita* is irrelevant to non-כשר *kosher* animals. So obviously the act
of שחיטה *shechita* will have no effect. The concept of שחיטה *shechita*
is relevant to כשר *kosher* animals because if it's not a טריפה
*treifa* it'll make it edible. So since the act of שחיטה *shechita*
is meaningful to change the status if it's not a טריפה *treifa*,
even when it is a טריפה *treifa*, שחיטה *shechita* should be significant
enough to take it out of the category of נבלה *neveila*. Now
again, maybe, okay, I can hear the logic of why, but again,
where, you know, you would think you would need a פסוק *pasuk*
or some evidence to hinge it on that says that there should
be some difference. Okay, it doesn't prove it, it just proves it's
a basis for a distinction, but it doesn't prove that you should
make that distinction. So but that's really where the משנה *Mishna* ends,
and it says since there, although we're not going to learn it
from a non-כשר *kosher* animal, שחיטה *shechita* is irrelevant there, since שחיטה
*shechita* is relevant for כשר *kosher* animals we will say that even
if the animal's a טריפה *treifa*, it is since שחיטה *shechita* is
relevant and you did שחיטה *shechita*, it's enough to make it not
a נבלה *neveila*. And now it ends by saying, בן שמונה חי
*ben shmonah chai*. If an animal is born in the eighth month,
remember the Rabbis understood that an eighth-month animal was not viable, an
eighth-month child is not viable, so even if it's born it's considered
to be essentially like it's already a נבלה *neveila*, okay? שחיטה *shechita*
will not have any effect on this even if it's not a
טריפה *treifa* whatever, it's basically not viable. So it's like it's already
dead, it's already a נבלה *neveila*. So in that case, אין שחיטתו
מטהרתו *ein shechitatu metaharatu*, the שחיטה *shechita* does not make it טהור
*tahor*, לפי שאין במינו שחיטה *lefi she-ein be-mino shechita*. There is not
שחיטה *shechita* in its מין *min*. Now that's not really what it,
technically correct, because it's still a cow, there's still שחיטה *shechita* by
cows, and if you mean שחיטה *shechita* was never relevant for it,
or שחיטה *shechita* was never relevant for an animal that was born
a טריפה *treifa*, right, and we exactly said that's not considered a
different מין *min*, that's considered the cow still שחיטה *shechita* relevant in
this instantiation, right, there is no, you know, there is no שחיטה
*shechita*, but it's still relevant for cows. So here why don't we
say the same thing? Either to take the משנה *Mishna* at its
literal level, it really thinks that the idea of things born in
the eighth month create a special מין *min* all to themselves, which
would be very, very strange, or it's a little לאו דווקא *lav
davka* here, and what it really means is since it's not considered
viable and it's like it's considered already dead, so therefore it's going
to be considered a נבלה *neveila* because שחיטה *shechita* doesn't work on,
is not meaningful to something that's already effectively dead. Okay, so if
you went ahead and you took an animal that had actually already
died, and you went and did a שחיטה *shechita* on it, it
obviously wouldn't work. So the same is if you do a שחיטה
*shechita* on this. Okay, so this משנה *Mishna*, the end, lays the
foundation that שחיטה *shechita*, if you do a שחיטה *shechita* on a
טריפה *treifa* it's not טמא tamei *tamei*. We're saying at least there's
a logic why it's different than a non-כשר *kosher* animal, but not
proving that it should be different. And the, this beginning is the
debate of the status of the limb. Is the limb for which
שחיטה *shechita* didn't work, do we say that שחיטה *shechita* never related
to it at all and it's like a נבלה *neveila*, or do
we say it related but wasn't effective?
אמאי Amai, says the גמרא: Gemara Why, even when
you—so the גמרא Gemara says let’s see for argument’s sake רבי מאיר’s
Rabbi Meir point that the limb is a נבלה. So you שחט
shechted the mother, you now have meat touching this limb, this limb
is a נבלה, the meat now gets the טומאה tumah of touching
a נבלה. But the גמרא Gemara, says
even before you cut it off?
What? You שחט shechted the mother, you didn’t cut it off. The
limb is sticking out, you שחט the mother, you now have a
dead cow with a fetus inside and it’s all meat and an
arm sticking out of the womb. That arm sticking out is a
נבלה for רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, and it makes the fetus inside
טמא tamei because it’s touching the fetus.
It’s also touching the mother.
It’s also touching the mother, but it also makes the fetus inside,
that’s the most immediate thing it’s touching, okay? So imagine, it makes
the fetus טמא tamei because of its טומאה. tumah So says the
גמרא, Gemara. why does it make the fetus טמא tamei. because it’s
touching it? But wait a minute, where’s it touching it? It’s all
attached. So the point of touch is really a non-exposed part of
the body, right? If you think about my arm, right, this is
touching my shoulder, but where’s it touching my shoulder? If you cut
it off, the surfaces are touching,
right, but right now it’s attached, so the surface touching is a
בית הסתרים beit hasetarim is a hidden place. There’s no exposed flesh
that’s touching one another. Okay, so why does it transfer טומאה tumah,
to the fetus?
Right, if the limb happens to also be touching the mother’s womb
and whatever, which it probably is, it’s probably not just suspended in
there, we can accept that it transfers טומאה tumah to the mother,
right, because the exposed skin of the limb is touching the exposed
skin of the womb, but in terms of the fetus, it’s only
the hidden surfaces are touching. That is not—that’s not—to transfer טומאה, tumah
yes.
That’s assuming the fetus is dead at that point and not alive.
That’s true, the fetus in theory could be alive and then it
wouldn’t be טמא tamei because live things don’t become טמא. tamei. But
we’re assuming it’s dead, correct.
Just the way the arm would be in that position, it’s just
more likely to be dead. Exactly, exactly.
We could assume it’s alive but then it certainly wouldn’t be טמא
tamei and the משנה says that it is טמא. tamei? So we’re
assuming that it’s dead. So let’s see the גמרא. Gemara אמאי, why
is the fetus טמא tamei by its limb? טומאת בית הסתרים היא,
tumat beit hasetarim hi, it is a טומאה tumah that is touched
in a hidden space. Now again, that’s different than טומאה בלועה. tumah
beluah. טומאה בלועה tumah beluah means the טומאה tumah doesn’t exist at
all, right, even if it’s something like that causes טומאה tumah in
a room, it’s a טומאה tumah, of a corpse. But here, it’s
not a question, the טומאה tumah. is out in the air, it
can create טומאה, tumah
but is this considered an act of touching? Act of touching has
to
be—it cannot be a נגיעת בית הסתרים, negiyat beit hasetarim, cannot be
touching on a hidden surface, it has to be touching an exposed
surface. So this is not before like טומאה בלועה, tumah beluah, that
was about the whole object of like it didn’t exist, this is
about the act of touching. So the גמרא Gemara says this is
touching of a hidden surface. וטומאת בית הסתרים, v'tumat beit hasetarim, and
the touching of a hidden surface לא מטמאה, lo m'tamia, does not
cause טומאה. tumah So how do you explain why the fetus is
טמא? tamei. So לימא רבי מאיר לטעמיה, leima Rabbi Meir l'taameih, maybe
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir goes according to his reasoning, which is what?
דתנן, detnan, we taught in the משנה: שלשה על שלשה שנחלק טהור
מן המדרס אבל טמא מגע מדרס דברי רבי מאיר. shlosha al shlosha
shenichlak tahor min hamidras aval tamei maga midras divrei Rabbi Meir. A
garment to be considered a garment at all has to be three
fingers width by three fingers width. So what would you say this
is—about two inches, three inches, something like that? Anyway, let’s say about
two inches by two
inches. שלוש על שלוש אצבעות. shalosh al shalosh etzbaot. For to be
bigger enough to be considered a type of a sit to be
sat on, a seat, it has to be שלשה טפחים על שלשה
טפחים, shlosha tefachim al shlosha tefachim, about nine inches by nine inches.
Now why does it matter that it’s a seat? Because if you
have something like a זב zav or a זבה, zavah, right, they
cause טומאה tumah not by touch, if they touch a something then
they’re an אב av and the thing becomes a ראשון, rishon, one
degree
lower. Here, however, they sit on something, right, and the תורה Torah
speaks about משכב ומושב mishkav u'moshav which the רבנים Rabbanim call מדרס,
midras, something that is trampled on, meaning whatever sat on, then it
becomes an אב, av, it does not go down a level. So
a זב zav is an אב, av, if he sits on a
seat, the seat is an אב. av. So now you have a
זב zav sat on a cloth. It was שלשה טפחים על שלשה
טפחים, shlosha tefachim al shlosha tefachim, big enough to be considered a
seat. And now what you did is you tore it in half.
So it no longer is a seat, it stops being an אב
הטומאה. av hatumah. What happens to half of the cloth? Okay, it
used to be an אב, av, now it was torn in half,
what happens to it? So the question is maybe it has the
טומאה tumah, of having touched an אב הטומאה. av hatumah. Okay, where
did it touch an אב הטומאה? av hatumah? Well, it touched the
other half as you were tearing it. Okay, so it was sort
of touching itself or touching the other half of the cloth as
it was sort of being torn and maybe even though it’s no
longer an אב, av, since it’s שלוש על שלוש אצבעות shalosh al
shalosh etzbaot big enough to still be טמא tamei but not a
seat, right, it at least has the טומאה tumah, of having touched
an אב. av. So there you have the idea that even though
something is completely attached, it’s considered like it’s touching the thing it’s
attached to, and therefore... it's enough to transfer.
I thought destroying things, I felt like kind of gets rid of
טומאה, tumah sort of like כלי חרס. keli cheres.
Not if what remains is still fit to become טמא. tamei. Then
the question is, does it have some residual טומאה, tumah which is
exactly what we're discussing? So let's take a look. So maybe Rabbi
Meir is going to his reasoning: that because we taught: שלשה על
שלשה, shlosha al shlosha, you have something that is three by three
טפחים tefachim big enough to be a seat and is an אב,
av, שנחלק, shenechlak, and then it was split in half, it was
ripped in half. טהור מן המדרס, tahor min hamidras, it no longer
is a מדרס, midras, a מושב, moshav, which would be an אב
הטומאה, av hatumah, אבל טמא מגע מדרס, aval tamei maga midras, it
has the טומאה tumah of one degree removed because it touched the
מדרס. midras. דברי רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir Now, what did it touch?
דתניא אמר רבי יוסי, detanya amar Rabbi Yose, so that's what Rabbi
Yose says, וכי באיזה מדרס נגע זה? vechi be'eizeh midras naga zeh?
This half of a cloth, what מדרס midras did it touch? It
didn't touch something that was a מדרס, midras, it didn't touch a
מדרס, midras, right? אלא אם נגע בו זב שהיה טמא מגע זב.
ela im naga bo zav shehaya tamei maga zav. If a זב
zav had actually touched it, then it would be טמא tamei as
one degree because—no, or even before he ripped it. He says like
this: A זב zav could sit on it without touching it, right?
He could sit on it if he's with his clothes on. So
then it only gives it the status of a מושב. moshav. It
never gets its status of טומאה tumah through contact with a זב.
zav. But let's say the זב zav happened to sit on it,
stand on it with his bare feet, or you know, first he
touched it then he sat on it. Then it has two statuses
coexisting. Then it's both a מדרס midras and something that touched a
זב, zav, which is one degree removed. Now you split it in
half, it loses its מדרס midras status, it's not big enough, but
it retains that lesser status because it had touched a זב zav
and that טומאה tumah remains even though it's a smaller size. So
Rabbi Yose says, I will concede the point that it is a
ראשון rishon if it had both statuses going beforehand. If it both
was sat on by a זב, zav, which made it an אב,
av, and it touched a זב, zav, which made it a ראשון.
rishon. Now you cut it in half, it's no longer a seat,
it's no longer an אב, av, it retains its ראשון. rishon. That's
if it had both statuses. But if all it was was a
seat, the זב zav sat on it with his clothes on and
all it was was a seat, you tear it in half, it's
no longer a seat, end of story. It didn't touch a seat,
it was a seat, so end of story. So Rabbi Meir says,
no, no, it touched itself. So Rabbi Meir has this concept that
something could be considered touching itself even though it was really all
attached. Okay.
Any skin contact, or hands and feet specifically?
Any skin contact. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says, so it
seems like our משנה is Rabbi Meir and therefore the same by
the fetus. It touches itself and therefore that's why it can cause
טומאה tumah. even though it's not exposed. So the גמרא Gemara says,
you like that? So the גמרא Gemara, says, לא איתמר עלה, lo
itmar alah,
wait one minute says the גמרא, Gemara... we can have this going
even according to Rabbi Yose. Why? אמר עולא, amar Ulla, because Ulla
said, it was said on this that Ulla said, לא שנו אלא
שלשה על שלשה שנחלק. lo shanu ela shlosha al shlosha shenechlak. When
is there this debate between Rabbi Meir and Rabbi Yose? When it's
a size of a seat, three by three, that was cut. So
it stopped being a מדרס midras in the very process. אבל שלשה
על שלשה הבא מבגד גדול, aval shlosha al shlosha haba mibeged gadol,
if you tore a little piece off of a huge cloth,
בשעת פרישתן מאביהן מקבלות טומאה מאביהן. besha'at perishatan me'avihen mekablot tumah me'avihen.
So when they are separating from their father, they receive טומאה tumah
from their father. What does this mean? It means part of the
problem of tearing this thing in half is not just that the
remnant cloth never touched anything, it's that in the process of making
it a half of a cloth, you were—the seat was going out
of existence, right? So you were destroying it from being a seat.
What happens if, if we use my office, okay, sorry, what happens
if you have a cloth, a huge cloth, you got a blanket,
okay, you got a big blanket and you're tearing a little corner
off of the blanket, three, a three, three אצבעות, etzbaot, not big
enough to be a seat but big enough to be טמא. tamei.
In that case, okay, what remains is still a מדרס, midras, what
remains is still a seat. Right here, the seat goes out of
existence. So in that case, says Ulla, even Rabbi Yose would agree.
Even Rabbi Yose would agree, you tear off this little piece of
a blanket, it is touching the, you know, the mother ship, and
in that case it is טמא tamei through touching. Rabbi Yose disagreed
not because there was no touching, but because when it started being
its own piece of cloth, the whole idea of—the whole cloth stopped
being a seat. But if the whole cloth remains a seat and
this is being torn off, then it is, does transfer טומאה. tumah.
And it says, and that's basically the case of our משנה, because
when you, if you were to cut a limb off of the
fetus, the fetus still, you know, still exists and the fetus still,
can become טמא. tamei So he says, הכא נמי, hacha nami, here
too, בשעת פרישה מאבר מקבל טומאה מאבר, besha'at perisha me'eiver mekabel tumah
me'eiver, when the fetus is separating from the limb, it gets טומאה
tumah from the limb. So he said, it was very nice that
whole fascinating debate about cutting the whole cloth in half, but the
reason Rabbi Yose argued was also because the seat stopped existing. But
if you had something that was one big piece and you tore
a little bit off... And the other thing was still considered to
have its original status, right, then certainly it would transfer טומאה. tumah
So here when you separate the אבר, it's not so it's not
so small, the עובר, ubar, the fetus from the limb, limb retains
its status. So since the limb retains its status as a נבילה
neveilah or as a you know, as a נבילה, neveilah, it will
then transfer when you're cutting it off to the you know, to
the fetus. Now, working back, one minute. Now, the question is, why
is that? Is that because we say it doesn't matter that it's
טומאת בית הסתרים, tumat beit hastarim, that it's נגיעת בית הסתרים? negiyat
beit hastarim? I mean, what happens to the problem that they're that's
still the touch only occurred at the surfaces that were not exposed?
So here רש''י Rashi says, no, once we're saying this, we're actually
saying that it's not because of the touch that they did at
the time. As you're cutting off this cloth from, you know, the
other cloth, it's going to touch, right, not while it's attached and
it's בית הסתרים, beit hastarim, but you make your little cut, right,
so there's some part of the cloth, some part of this little
piece that you're cutting away is going to touch the original. Or,
you cut the limb away from the fetus. As you're cutting it
away, it's impossible that it that wasn't a moment where the cut
surface went ahead and went back and touched the actual fetus itself.
So we're actually not saying that it was the touch that occurred
when they were combined, that is בית הסתרים, beit hastarim, but as
you're cutting it off and in the process of removing it, we're
going to assume that there will be some surface contact. That's at
least the way רש''י Rashi explains. It's not the touch that occurred
when it was one integral piece.
רבי מאיר is fine with that.
Or רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi.
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is fine in general, but he says, but
if you're destroying the original thing in the process, then it's irrelevant.
If you're tearing the seat, so there's no seat anymore to transfer
טומאה tumah in the process of tearing the thing in half. That's
his whole issue. Okay? Let's
that's one explanation, that as you're cutting it, it will touch in
the process.
So the עובר ubar becomes טמא tamei. through the limb?
Yes. From touching the limb.
But here in the original case, it's the other way around. The
limb becomes...
Right, it doesn't matter bigger or small. The question is, does the
thing that is טמא still carry its status? Okay. You could also
imagine that you left a little blanket three by three טפחים tefachim
and you tore away a size that was twenty טפחים tefachim big.
It doesn't it's not relative size, it's whether the thing that causes
טומאה still retains its status. Okay, so now we'll have one we'll
read one other answer and then we'll end with that for today.
רבינא אמר, Ravina amar, רבינא Ravina said, בגד לאו לחתיכה קאי. beged
lav lechaticha kai.
There could be a debate by the sheet. Even if you don't
accept עולא, Ulla, there could be a debate whether the sheet is
considered touching itself. Why? Because you're not in the you know, it's
not like
it's not like fit to be cut. It's not ready to be
cut. All right, there could be exceptions, but as a general rule,
just cause you have one piece of cloth, you don't say it's
touching itself because you don't conceptually see that there's something separate here
that you can conceptually call it touching the larger part. You see
it as one integral unit. Maybe there are exceptions, but as a
general rule. However, עובר לחתיכה קאי. ubar lechaticha kai.
A limb sticking out of a fetus, especially since you can't eat
the limb, you can eat the fetus, but you can't eat the
limb. So conceptually, that limb you already see it as something that
has to be cut away. Since you already see it as something
that has to be cut away, then therefore what? Therefore you consider
it as if you've already cut it and as if now it's
just, you know, against it's touching the touching the fetus, but not
that it's all one integral unit. You see it as already cut
and it's no longer בית הסתרים.
beit hastarim. If you're an account or feel...
No, no, no, this was the limb that was sticking out. So
that can't be eaten. The fetus can be eaten. Okay. Oh, you're
saying you might not choose not to eat the fetus? Maybe, but
at least you שחט the mother, so we're looking at it
through that lens. Okay. וכל העומד לחתוך כחתוך דמי. ve-khol ha-omed lachtokh
ke-khatukh dami. And
anything that is standing that is in the pro... you know, about
to be cut off, is ready to be cut off, it's like
it's already cut off. And therefore he says, we can call it
that it's not a touching of בית הסתרים beit hastarim because if
you imagine that it's already cut off, then if it's already cut
off, it already has its exposed surface and now the surfaces are
touching one another. So it's as if you already have two exposed
surfaces which are touching because you imagine this as if it's already
cut off. What?
Therefore it does transfer. That explains.
Why? What?
And how do you if
it's טומאה is not the same as כשרות. kashrus. Definitely not neither.
And you can eat something טמא. Right. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. So the
גמרא... okay, so we will pick up with this tomorrow and see
this principle of something standing to be cut off is like it
is already cut off.